Good morning, Canvas Church. Thanks so much for joining us for Church Online this week.
Pastor Ryan here. If you haven't met me yet, I'm so glad that you are joining us. This is probably the first time many of you are seeing me in a while, just recovering from COVID and the holidays. I haven't been around much digitally since we haven't been in person, but I miss seeing you guys. Super thankful that we have the technology that we can meet online, even when we can't meet in person.
We'd love to have you come out to Canvas Connection if you're new or newer to meet us and to talk to us about our church and what that looks like moving forward.
Obviously, it's great to be back. This year started out for our church and for me and for probably a lot of you a lot differently than maybe we anticipated or expected, but I am optimistic and believing that God is at work in the midst of our church.
The reality is churches aren't built on our names or our staff or our branding or our building. Churches are made up of individual believers gathered together around the mission of God.
Ephesians says that for each of us as individuals, God has prepared good works in advance for us to do. I'm just believing that as a church coming together with other individual believers that God has good works planned for us as a church to do moving forward in 2022.
So I'm excited to discover that together as a church. And normally I prepare sermon series kind of a few months in advance based on a number of different variables as we pray and seek the Lord and we try and cover Old Testament books and New Testament books and we try and kind of holistically teach through the Bible in a really well thought out way.
As we're kind of responding to an unexpected situation in our church with Pastor Brandon's resignation is just to take a couple of weeks into a week by week sermon series and just pray and seek the Lord and whoever might be speaking that week, whether it be someone from the leadership team or me or a guest speaker, whatever it might be that I'm kind of entitling this sermon series, God Only Knows. I think about that old, is it Beach Boys song, right? Like God Only Knows.
Speaking to us, we're seeking the Lord and asking what word do you have for us this week? What might you be challenging us as a church to do and how can we respond to it? So over the next couple of weeks, we're just going to be really seeking the Lord. Not that we don't do that every week, we do, but week to week rather than month to month or series to series. For the next couple of weeks, I just want to week to week seek the Lord together and ask what God might have for us. So that's kind of the direction that we're going to be heading over the next couple of weeks.
to hear what God has for us. Let me pray, and then we'll hop into what I feel like God is leading me to share this morning. Father, we are so thankful that we worship a sovereign God who is sitting on his throne, ruling and reigning, and that you are in charge and over everything that we experience. And ultimately, God, one day you're going to return and make all things new. And we long for and hope for that day, especially in the midst of all of the
sickness that surrounds our world right now. We long for a day when there will be no more crying or pain or sickness because you return and make all things as they are meant to be. But until that day comes, God, you ask us to live on mission, to point others to you in the midst of that. And so God, this morning, I pray that you would speak to us from your word. I pray that you would have a word for us specifically this morning, that each of us would feel like we leave this place hearing from you
and knowing what you're calling us to do this week. It's in Jesus' name I pray. Amen.
Well, if you have your Bibles or a Bible app, I'd love to have you follow along with me. We're going to be in the book of Philemon, the very popular, well-known book of Philemon. It's towards the end of the New Testament, if you're new to the Bible. It's a very short book of the Bible, and it illustrates for us this principle. It's a Bible study principle.
When we read Scripture, especially in New Testament letters, we're reading other people's mail. What we're going to see here in the book of Philemon is Paul writing a letter specifically to an individual named Philemon. It really helps us to understand that Bible study principle that when we read Scripture, yes, Scripture is God-breathed. It's given to us by God, but it's also a collection of letters that were written to specific people at a specific time for a specific purpose. When we draw application out, we're not reading this as if it's God's
direct word to us, but we're reading it as if it's these letters that were written to these people at this specific time. And then from there, we ask God to give us what it means to us and how we can apply those principles in our life. And there's all kinds of potential applications that you could get from Philemon as I was studying it and listening to other sermons and sermons on all kinds of different things from the book of Philemon. It's a small, unique book that you can draw out a ton of different applications.
Thank you, Lord, leading me to share from Philemon. I just kept hearing over and over and over again that this book models for us how to have unifying conversations in the midst of difficult and emotionally charged disagreements. So I think what we can learn from this letter that Paul writes to Philemon is we can learn some principles for how to have unifying conversations. How believers in Christ can have unifying conversations, even in the midst of difficult and emotional conversations.
emotionally charged disagreements. The reality is our culture and the church in America right now is so divided along emotionally charged issues. And the church is supposed to have a countercultural unity in the midst of diversity, but I'm afraid that far too often the church in America, we sell out. We sell out countercultural unity for the sake of uniformity. Like we don't work hard to have diverse relationships
with other followers in Christ that we have disagreements with because it's more comfortable and it's more easy for us to just gather together with people that look like us, talk like us, think like us. And it's really easy, if we're not careful, to form echo chambers of people that think like us, talk like us, believe like us. But God has designed something so much more beautiful for the church. We're supposed to be the most ethnically diverse, the most socioeconomically diverse, the most just diverse group of people all
gathered around the message of Jesus. And when you gather diverse people with different backgrounds and experiences and thoughts, when you gather those people together, there are going to be tense situations, emotionally charged situations. And what tends to happen in those situations, if we're not careful, is we tend to avoid those situations. We tend to, again, gather together with people that agree with us, rather than to lean into those conversations, to be intentional, excuse me, to be intentional and to have
unifying conversations with people that we disagree with. And so I think this book of Philemon kind of gives us a peek behind the curtain, where Paul and Philemon are having this kind of emotionally charged conversation. They're going to have a conversation about a situation that they disagree on, and Paul is just going to shepherd Philemon and his family and the church through this conversation in a way that really helps us, I think, that application that we can get from reading this letter is some practical principles for how to
have unifying conversations in the midst of an emotionally charged disagreement. As I was thinking about my outline for this morning, I was reminded of one of my favorite episodes of one of my favorite TV shows, The Office. I don't know if we have any office people out there, but one of my favorite episodes of The Office is this episode called Conflict Resolution, where Michael Scott is helping Oscar and Angela work through this difficult conflict that they're having, and they pull out this binder from HR, right?
Any of us who have ever worked in a corporate setting or gone to school, there's often conflict resolution templates of how we can work through conflict and meet in the middle and have this conflict resolution. They open this binder, and the whole episode is them working through this conflict resolution. Obviously, there's a lose-lose situation. There's a win-lose situation. There's a win-win situation.
There's ultimately a situation where it's win-win-win, where nobody loses. What I don't want us to do with this book is look at it like that binder, where you look and you say, "Well, if a person does this, then we respond this way." If they think this, and it's like tabs, you flip the tabs on the binder and you just do a carbon copy response. That's not what I want to get from this letter. I want to just walk through a carbon copy conversation of Paul and Philemon and say, "Well, since Paul did this, we should do this."
But I think there are a couple really practical principles that can help us frame up conversations that we have, tense conversations with other believers in Christ, and how we can have unity in the midst of those tense conversations. That's kind of the direction we're going to be heading the rest of our time together. I will remind you that I am still recovering from being sick, so I feel like I'm being kind of monotone and I might even be visibly sweating on camera. I'm sorry.
I'm getting there. But that's kind of the direction we're going to be headed this morning. And again, just for some context, Paul is writing this letter to his good friend Philemon, and Paul has randomly connected with—this is where it's going to get tense really quick—Paul has randomly connected with one of Philemon's runaway slaves, a guy by the name of Onesimus, who was a slave of Philemon, who had, it looks like, actually stolen from Philemon, stolen from his family, and ran away from Philemon.
And immediately, those of us that live in America in 2022, we immediately have a tension about us because we're like, "Oh, here we go. I knew it. I knew the Bible was antiquated. I knew the Bible was misogynistic, and it propped up slavery." And we tend to buy into this narrative, but the reality of—I just really—we don't have time to get into all of the details around that, but just a quick point of clarification. This is a very different type of slavery than the slavery that we think about immediately when we think about
slavery. The slavery at this time was not racially driven. Many scholars estimate that around 80% of non-Roman citizens would be considered slaves, and this was, again, a really quick point of clarification. We don't have time to get into the weeds today, but let me be clear. The way of Jesus is unequivocally anti-slavery. Some passages in the Bible have been and can be misinterpreted, and the church has not always had the best
track record when it comes to dealing with some of those things, but the way of Jesus and the way of Scripture is unequivocally anti-slavery. And I also want to point out that it was followers of Jesus motivated by the Scriptures who were a big part in helping to abolish slavery in our country. So, again, we don't have time to get into the weeds, but you can feel the emotional tension of this conversation. I think the best way to kind of illustrate the type of relationship that Phileas
Philemon had with his friend Onesimus, this runaway slave that Paul met. I think about Amazon, right? And if you've followed the news at all, you've probably heard some pretty bad horror stories about how Amazon treats their employees. And that's kind of the situation that I think we could best model Philemon's relationship with Onesimus. Philemon had a financial agreement with Onesimus. Onesimus was being compensated for his work, but it probably wasn't
the most godly environment. Philemon probably wasn't being the best follower of Jesus in the way that he was interacting with Onesimus. And so there's tension on both sides. It's this emotionally driven situation. And the letter seems to indicate that Onesimus, at the time, he wasn't a follower of Jesus. And he obviously had some problems with his relationship with Philemon. So he probably looks like he stole from Philemon and ran away.
So no phones, no cars, no internet. It could have been really easy for Onesimus to never have to have a conversation with Philemon again. Just leave that relationship, avoid that relationship forever. But this is really important. Paul, a leader in the New Testament church, he understands that this tension is an opportunity for both Philemon and for Onesimus to be conformed into the image of Jesus. And so it's like Paul here is forcing Philemon and Onesimus
to come together and to have this really uncomfortable conversation in this really emotionally tense situation. But the reality is oftentimes tense conflicts with other followers of Jesus provide for us a unique opportunity to fight for unity and to be conformed to the image of Jesus. That's why I think it's so important for us to look through this book this morning because I think in our culture it's so easy for us to just avoid
difficult conversations to avoid. Anytime there's tension in a relationship for us to be like, you know what, I'm not really interested in that. But I think by Paul sitting down to write this letter to force this conversation between Philemon and Onesimus, a conversation that really didn't have to happen, I think what we'll see here is that it's important to have those conversations. When the tension arises, it's important to fight for unity with people that we might not disagree with but that are followers of Jesus.
Let's work through this short book and see if we can't draw out a few principles for how to have a unifying conversation with believers who are in a tense situation.
In verse 1, and we don't even have to have chapters because it's one chapter, so in verse 1 it says, "This letter is from Paul, a prisoner for preaching the good news about Christ Jesus, and from our brother Timothy. I am writing to Philemon, our beloved co-worker, and our sister, Apphia, and to our fellow soldier,
Archippus, and to the church that meets in our house. May God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ give grace and peace to all of you." So I think the first principle we can draw out from this conversation is that when we have tense disagreements with other followers of Jesus, when there's tension, when there's difficulty, and we feel the need to have a unifying conversation, it's really important that we invite outside perspective. Invite an outside perspective into the conversation.
You see here he says to Philemon, so that's the main person that he wants to address, and to Apphia and Archippus is most likely Philemon's wife and son. They would all kind of have the same perspective about this situation. But then he says, "And to the church that meets in their house." See, I think Paul included the church that meets in their house because he knew that it would be really easy for Philemon and Philemon's wife and Philemon's son to have a very similar perspective, a very similar way of looking
at this situation. It could be easy for them to kind of form their own little echo chamber and say, "No, you don't understand. We had this financial agreement with Onesimus, and he broke it, and he ran away, and he stole from our family." It could be really easy for them to get together in this kind of echo chamber of the same perspective. But Paul knew that in order for unity to happen in this tense situation, that it was important for him to bring in other people that are in relationship to Philemon and Onesimus that might have a different
perspective. Paul knew that inviting church members into the conversation would provide multiple perspectives and points of view into the conversation. Like I said earlier, the church is meant to be one of the most ethnically, socioeconomically, gender, race, diverse group of people in the world. Galatians chapter 3 says there's neither Jew, Gentile, male, female, slave, free. The church was designed by God to be the most ethnically, socially, and economically diverse place on
the planet. And so there is going to be tension. There are going to be disagreements, but we have to avoid just getting together with the people that see things from our perspective. We have to invite outside perspective into the conversation. And bringing in other perspectives helps us keep the main thing the main thing. It helps us to realize and step outside of just our perspective and keep our focus on the kingdom and keep our focus on the gospel.
Excuse me. Unity in the kingdom of God often takes priority over our personal preferences, and unity in the kingdom of God often takes sacrificial love.
I think about Jesus' famous teaching on the Sermon on the Mount when he tells us to turn the other cheek. Oftentimes when there's tension, when there's difficult conversations to be had, the best thing that we can do is sacrificially give up our own preferences in order to serve someone else. That's the example we've been given.
in Jesus. And so, if we're facing an emotionally charged disagreement, we should invite someone from the outside of the situation to add some less emotionally charged perspectives to the conversation. That's what Paul does. He brings in the church that meets at their house.
Moving on in verse four through seven, I think we'll see that another principle for these unifying conversations is the foundation for tense conversations in the family of God should be built on prayer and honor.
Excuse me. In verse four, it says, "I always thank my God when I pray for you, Philemon." Paul says, "Philemon, I'm regularly praying for you because I keep hearing about your faith in the Lord Jesus and your love for all of God's people. And I am praying that you will put into action the generosity that comes from your faith as you understand and experience all the good things we have in Christ. Your love has given me such joy and comfort, my brother, for your kindness has often refreshed the hearts
of God's people." So as Paul is getting into this tense conversation with Philemon, he makes it clear that before he enters this conversation, he's intentionally been praying for Philemon, and then he goes out of his way to point out some positive characteristics. He goes out of his way to honor Philemon, to honor Philemon's faith, to honor Philemon's relationship with God. Before Paul ever decides to write this letter, he's regularly and intentionally praying.
When we think about these tense conversations that we enter into with other believers, if we aren't willing to pray for the person that God's leading us into these conversations with, then we shouldn't even consider having the conversation at all. We should always go into these conversations first with prayer. And sometimes prayer's the end of it. Sometimes we're really spun up and emotionally charged about a disagreement
that we're having with another follower of Jesus, and we begin to pray for them. And ultimately, through prayer, God turns our heart and He helps us to see that person's perspective. And we're like, "You know what? I overreacted. I need to get over this. I don't even need to have a conversation." Sometimes by praying for that person, we'll realize that the conversation isn't even necessary. I wonder how many petty disagreements and broken relationships would never have happened in the church if individuals were committed
to stopping and praying for people that they're struggling with. So first, we pray for those individuals that we're struggling with. And the second is we choose to honor them. If after praying for them, you still feel led to have a conversation about this tension, which I think is important. It's good to have these conversations. We should start the conversation with intentional honor. Romans 12 says that we should outdo one another in showing honor.
When we honor people from the very outset, this immediately disarms the tension of the rest of the conversation. And the reality is we can always find a way to honor people. I think Paul clearly has an issue with Philemon's business handlings, but from the outset he says, "Hey, here's all of these positive things that I know to be true about you and your faith and your relationship with God." And so starting with those things disarms the conversation from the beginning.
I have a specific person in mind that I'm thinking about when I share this illustration. There's this friend of mine on Facebook, and she lives on the West Coast, and she has a different ideology and perspective than I do. She's a follower of Jesus, and we have really good conversations on social media about pretty heated topics. And the reality is I think the reason that these conversations always go so well is because any time
I sit down and reply to a post that she has, I always start the post with some type of honor, some type of, "Hey, I think I see where you're coming from here. I think I understand why you're saying this or why you believe this, but I have this question. I need you to help me understand where you're coming from." Or, "Hey, it seems to me like you're saying this. Is this what you're actually saying?" And honestly, we've never had a bad conversation on social media. And I know for some of you that might sound crazy because all you know
is negative conversations on social media. But the reality is, I'm trying to shepherd people in the way that I use my social media page. Because if we're not careful, social media, it disciples us to dehumanize people. And without realizing it, we immediately just de-honor people by dehumanizing them. We treat people as if they're just some nameless, faceless thing behind a computer screen, and we don't treat people with honor.
But I think as we enter into these tough conversations, we should always bake it in prayer and begin those conversations, finding a way to honor these people. And what I would say is we're not whitewashing the area of tension. Excuse me. We're choosing to believe the best about someone, and we're setting a positive tone for a potentially negative conversation. So, pray. And if you still decide that you need to have the conversation, choose to
initiate the conversation with honor. Find something that you can positively point out about this brother and sister in Christ as you enter into this tough conversation. He goes on after including other people with an outside perspective and spending time in prayer and then starting with honor. He then goes on to try and ultimately work hard to understand both perspectives in the conversation. Paul says,
in favor of you. I could demand it in the name of Christ because it's the right thing for you to do. I love that Paul's like, hey, I'm in charge of the churches around here. Like, I could command you to do this thing, but rather I want to invite you into this conversation. He says, "Because of your love, I prefer to simply ask you, consider this as a request from me, Paul, an old man who is a prisoner for the sake of Christ Jesus. I appeal to you to show kindness to my child, Onesimus.
I became his father in the faith while I'm here in prison." Let me get a drink of water real quick. I think this is an important perspective to point out because Paul's saying, look, Onesimus is now a brother in Christ. Like, he wasn't a follower of Jesus when he stole from you and when he fled from your house, but now he's become a follower of Jesus. That's an important perspective for you to understand. Onesimus was operating without an understanding of the gospel, and now
he has an understanding of the gospel. Make sure you understand that perspective. He says, Onesimus hasn't been of much use to you in the past. Again, he's acknowledging, I understand the tension that you have. I understand that he did some bad things to you and your family. He hasn't been of much use to you, but now I'm sending him back to you, and with him comes my own heart. I wanted to keep him here while I am in the chains for preaching the good news, and he would have helped me on your behalf, but I didn't want to do anything without your connection.
Again, Paul is shepherding Philemon through this. He's saying, "Look, I could have just kept him. You never would have known that I had him here. He could have just been helpful to me." But this tension, this emotionally-driven situation, provides an opportunity for both of you to grow in your faith.
He says, "But I didn't want to do anything without your consent. It seems you lost Onesimus for a little while, so that you could have him back forever. He is no longer like a slave to you. He is more than a slave, for he is a beloved.
He is a beloved brother, especially to me. Now he will mean much more to you, both as a man and as a brother in the Lord. So if you consider me your partner, welcome him as you welcome me."
So Paul here is really fighting to understand both perspectives. He's bringing Philemon to the table. He's saying, "Listen, yes, Onesimus made some bad decisions. He did some bad things that placed this tension in the relationship. But also, this relationship that you had with him was
unhealthy. And now that he's a brother in Christ, this should help you to see that you should treat him as a brother in Christ." Paul's working hard to understand both perspectives. He could have just commanded Philemon, "Hey, I'm in charge. Do this." But instead, he's inviting Philemon into this tension, into this process. We go back to the Michael Scott illustration, right? Like, Paul could have just commanded Philemon, "Hey, you're going to leave Onesimus with me. You're going to forgive all of his debts. We're going to wipe this thing away."
It's a win-win situation. But by inviting Philemon and Onesimus to be back into relationship with one another and to wrestle through the pain and the hurt that they've both caused one another, Paul views this as a win-win-win. Like, it's a win all around. Yes, it's difficult in the moment. The conversation is hard, but ultimately, it's going to lead to good. And something I want to point out here, the word Onesimus, Onesimus' name,
actually means useful. And so, Paul's pointing a pretty redemptive picture here when he says, "At one time, Onesimus wasn't useful to you, but now he is useful to you." And so, in the Greek, literally how that would read is useful, Onesimus, he wasn't useful, and now he's become useful. It's this redemptive picture. And that's kind of the redemption plan of us as human beings.
And then sin enters the world, and we become broken and sinful, but then through Jesus, we become useful yet again. And so, Paul's working hard to level the playing field here and to help them see each other's perspectives. When we enter into tense conversations, emotionally charged conversations, we have to work hard to enter into those tense conversations, having a hopeful view of the outcome, and fighting to understand the other person's perspective.
I say here, don't feel like you have to walk away from a tense conversation completely agreeing with the other person's perspective, but fight to understand their perspective. Andy Stanley has this quote that I love, where he says, "If you ever say the statement, 'I don't understand how someone could believe this. I don't understand how someone could think this. I don't understand how someone could act this way.' He says, 'You're acknowledging that you have a problem.'" See, oftentimes we say that statement like, "The other person has a problem."
But when we say, "I don't understand how such and such could do such a thing," what we're saying is, "We don't understand." And in order for us to understand, we have to fight through those difficult situations, those tense conversations, and we have to seek to understand their perspective. The reality is there might be a really good reason that they think that way, believe that way. Or there might be a bad reason that they don't understand. Maybe they're being influenced by a negative experience and they don't even realize it, and God is using that tense conversation to
to grow both of you in that situation. So going on in verse 17 through 20, it says, "So if you consider me a partner, welcome Onesimus as you would welcome me. If he has wronged you in any way or owes you anything, charge it to me. I, Paul, write this in my own hand. I will repay it, and I won't mention that you owe me your very soul. Yes, my brother, please do me this favor for the Lord's sake. Give me this
encouragement in Christ." So I think one of the last principles we can get here from this difficult conversation is ultimately the gospel should be the unifying force behind every tense conversation we have with another believer. This is Paul's only letter where he doesn't expressly refer to Christ or the cross. But make no mistake about it, he is reminding Philemon of the gospel.
"Receive Onesimus as you would receive me, and if he owes you anything, charge it to my account." Ultimately, he's reminding Philemon of the gospel, of the way that Jesus paid Philemon's price. He's saying, "Jesus paid the price for you when you couldn't afford it. Therefore, you should extend that same grace to Onesimus." But then he gets really pastoral and fatherly and kind of mean, which I like.
But like assertive, right? And he says, "Look, if you're not willing to extend that grace to him that you've received in Jesus, then charge it to my account. I'll pay his debts. I'll pay whatever he owes you. Me, the old guy who's in prison for preaching the gospel of Jesus." And so I'd say we should always put the pain and the tension of difficult conversations in the shadow of the cross. Like we should always, as we enter into tough, difficult conversations, we should always remember the gospel.
We should remember that Jesus paid the price for us when we didn't deserve it. This doesn't mean that we ignore pain or sin or injustice. Oftentimes, tense conversations come because someone has caused us pain. They've sinned against us. There's some injustice that we see. And that doesn't mean we ignore that, but we put that in perspective of the grace that we have received. Think about the pain and the tension that your sin caused the Father. Think about the pain and the tension that your
sin caused the Father, and yet he chose to send his one and only Son to pay your price for your sin. This is our example for tense conversations. Our example for tense conversations is extending grace and showing sacrificial love. I'm almost done. I know. I promise. Monotone message for 30 minutes is tough, but we're almost done. The last couple verses here, he says, "I'm confident as I write this letter that you will do what I ask and even more."
One more thing, please prepare a guest room for me, for I am hoping that God will answer your prayers, and let me return to see you soon. I think the last principle that we get from Paul's letter is, as we enter into tense conversations, as we deal with difficult situations with other believers, we should always prioritize a continued relationship. Paul enters this tense conversation with Philemon and Onesimus, again, a conversation that could have been avoided, but Paul says,
"No, it's valuable that we have this conversation. It's a win-win-win situation for all of us to come together and to deal with this. We can learn from this, we can grow from this, we can be sanctified through this conversation."
But then he says, again, they could have just had this one conversation, and then Onesimus could have went back to Paul, and Paul and Philemon never had to see each other ever again, but Paul says, "No, I'm coming to you. Prepare a bed for me. I'm going to continue in this relationship with you."
Even though we might disagree on how to handle this situation, I'm going to continue to prioritize my relationship with you.
We live in a culture that encourages us to cut ties with people that we have disagreements with, and this only increases our chances of ending up in an echo chamber.
Again, you don't have to be best friends with that person after a tense conversation, you don't have to get together with them for coffee every single week, but as followers of Jesus, we should always prioritize some type of continuity
relationship, some type of common ground, some unity for the sake of the gospel. See, the reason unity is so important is it's literally the apologetic of the church.
The last thing that Jesus prays before He goes to the cross in John 17 is that the church would be unified, and He says, by them being unified, the most ethnically, racially, socioeconomically diverse group of people on the planet, if they are able to have unity, that will demonstrate to
the rest of the world that my message is true, that I did rise from the dead. We have a unique cultural opportunity to model unity in the midst of diversity. So when we have these tense conversations, we have to prioritize a continued relationship. Even if we don't walk away agreeing 100% on everything, we walk away reminding ourselves that we are brothers and sisters under the banner of the message of Jesus.
Again, a unique cultural opportunity to model unity in diversity. And it won't happen if we hold grudges and avoid difficult conversations. It won't happen if we position ourselves in gossipy echo chambers. It won't happen if we continue to be discipled by social media to dehumanize people who think differently than us. We have to choose the less traveled path. We have to follow the example of Jesus. We have to lay down our preferences and to pursue the life-giving
world-changing unity for the sake of the gospel of Jesus. This is hard. People don't do this in our culture. We avoid conflict like the plague. We avoid emotionally tense conversations as much as we can. But as a body of Christ, we've been called to intentionally live into these conversations.
So, where do you have tension with other followers of Jesus? Who do you need to begin to regularly and intentionally
pray for? And maybe that's where it stops for you. Maybe you're identifying some people you're like, "Man, I've got some struggled relationships that I need to work on with brothers and sisters in Christ. I've got some disagreement here with these people or this ideology or this thought or this person." And God's bringing those people to your mind.
Begin to pray for them. And maybe through prayer you'll realize that it's really not that big of a deal and that you can move on. Or maybe through praying for them
you'll say like, "No, I need to step into this tense conversation that I don't really want to have, that I know is going to be good for me and good for them and good for the unity of the church." Who do you need to begin to regularly, intentionally pray for? What outside perspectives can you invite in? Maybe you begin to pray for somebody and you invite a godly friend or mentor in and say, "Hey, I have this tense relationship with this person. I'm not sure whether or not I should just let it go or engage them in a conversation. What do you think? What would you do if you were me?"
And then ultimately, who do you think you need to reach out to to have unifying conversations with that are built on the foundation of prayer and honor? I'm just believing this morning that the Holy Spirit is working in all of our hearts and that God's putting people into your mind that you can begin to pray for and maybe lean into those conversations. Don't ignore conviction. Do something about whoever those people are that God is bringing into your mind. My prayer for our church is that we would
be a church that doesn't settle for superficial niceties, but that we work hard to find unity in the midst of diversity. Man, that's like when my wife moved to this area, that was one of the things that she noticed about this kind of southern mentality that we have is we're really good at just niceties. Like we're really good at playing nice with everybody when in reality there's tension and there's broken relationships and there's definitely stuff going on there that
needs to be addressed, but in the south we just like pretend like it doesn't exist and we're just nice to everyone. Man, I'm praying that our church would fight against that, that we wouldn't just have superficial niceties, but that we'd have unity in the midst of diversity. And I'm crazy enough to believe that if we do this, that if we work hard at this, I'm crazy enough to believe that Jesus was right when he said that this type of unity would signal to the rest of the world that we have a message of hope that nothing else in this world can offer us.
church that fights for unity in the midst of tension and diversity, difficult conversations. And let's lay all of that under the umbrella of the gospel. Let's submit ourselves to the grace that we've received. Let's extend that grace to others. Let's fight for unity in the midst of diversity. Let's pray. Father, thank you for this church. Thank you for the opportunity that we have to engage with one another in relationship, God. And when we do that, tension happens.
disagreements happen. But I pray that we would be a church that fights for unity in the midst of diversity. Unity in the midst of tension and disagreement. That we would follow the example of Jesus. That we would sacrificially love and serve and pray for and honor one another in a way that ultimately glorifies you. It's in Jesus' name I pray. Amen.
Amen.